Guide to the Lack Temple B'nai Israel [Victoria, TX] Collection, 1877-2019 MS 902
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Lack Family/Temple B'nai Israel [Victoria, TX] collection
1877-2019
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Lack, Melvin
MS 902
.50 Linear Feet 1 box
1.25 Gigabytes Nearline access: MS902aip_001 (1.25 GB)
This collection is made up of one box containing administrative records, books, correspondences, news clippings, photographs, and programs from Temple B'nai Israel donated by the Lack Family, spanning from 1877-2019.
Biographical / Historical
Although the Jewish population numbered around 100 individuals, Victoria lacked a formal congregation until the end of the 19th century. While they had met together informally as early as the 1850s, they did not organize until 1867, when Victoria Jews established a Hebrew Benevolent Society. The society held services and even joined the Union of American Hebrew Congregations for several years in the 1880s. In 1876, Jewish women had founded the Hebrew Ladies' Benevolent Society, which had 17 members in 1900. They also founded a Jewish Children's Aid Society in 1889. A chapter of B'nai B'rith, later named in honor of prominent Jewish grocer Max Bettin, was organized in 1875. Finally, in 1894, Jews in Victoria established an official congregation, which they named B'nai Israel. Abraham Levi became its first President during these founding years and the first permanent Rabbi, George Solomon, arrived in Victoria in 1905. The synagogue that stands today was built in 1923 when the Jewish population in the city peaked at around 120 people. Today, there are about 20 Jewish families in Victoria. Dr. Shira Lander, a Southern Methodist University religion professor, has lead High Holiday services as well as periodic Shabbat and education services. Despite a 2007 incident in which the Temple's front was desecrated with anti-Semitic slurs, Victorian Jews remain welcome participants in the life of the city, and look to maintain their involvement and tradition in the coming years. Excerpt from: https://www.isjl.org/texas-victoria-encyclopedia.html
Born in 1942, Melvin Lack grew up in Victoria, Texas. His father was from Tulsa, Oklahoma, while his mother grew up in Houston, Texas. In 1938, Melvin's father decided to open a family business selling many goods such as toys, guns, and furniture. Growing up in Victoria, Melvin was one of only 30 Jewish kids in the community attending Sunday school at Temple B'nai Israel. As an undergraduate student, Melvin attended Rice University. While there, Melvin was heavily invested in extracurricular activities, joining the Student Council and Hillel, writing articles for The Rice Thresher, and serving as president of Weiss College. Once he received his Bachelor's degree in Economics, Melvin attended Harvard University Business School where he met his wife Janey, one of the first women to be admitted into the Business School in 1963. After convincing from his uncle, Melvin and his wife moved back to his hometown in 1969 to work for the family business. From there, the couple settled down and had three children - David, Jeffrey and Julie. For the next 40 years, the Lack Company thrived, opening 39 stores at its height. Meanwhile, Melvin became involved in the local Jewish community, serving on the Board of Directors for Congregation B'nai Israel for 35 years as well as serving several terms as president. In addition, Melvin helped raise money for the synagogue through Bingo fundraisers. This allowed for the synagogue to go through several renovations in the 1990s and establish its Endowment Fund. Today, Melvin remains in Victoria, TX, managing the real estate of the family while staying active on the stock market.
Scope and Contents
Administrative records, books, correspondences, news clippings, photographs, and programs document the lives of members of Temple B'nai Israel and their involvement in the Victoria Jewish community starting from its founding in 1872. Of particular interest is the original copy of the Constitution and by-laws of B'nai Israel in 1895, news clippings on famous Victoria Jewish pioneers, and a speech from Godcheaux L. Levi, a descendant of one of the early founders of B'nai Israel, to the Victoria Historical Society. This collection would be useful for researchers interested in the history of the Victorian Jewish community, early and recent publications, and the Temple B'nai Israel.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection open for research with restriction. For permission to access, contact Woodson Research Staff. Stored on-site at the Woodson Research Center.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Melvin Lack donated the papers in September of 2019.
Arrangement
The materials in this collection have been arranged in seven series as follows: Series I: Administrative Records; Series II: Books; Series III: Correspondences, Series IV: News Clippings; Series V: Photographs; Series VI: Programs, Series VII: History
Related Materials
Robert Levy Family paper (MS 831). Additional material can be obtained from the archives of the Texas Jewish Historical Society.
Index Terms
Subjects
Jews and Jewish life; History; Religion
Document Types
letters (correspondence); books; speeches; directories; programs (documents); photographs; newspapers
Places
Temple B'nai Israel
Subjects (Persons)
Lack, Melvin
Subjects (Corporations)
Congregation B'nai Israel (Victoria, Tex)
- Series I: Administrative Records, 1953-2019
  - B'nai Israel Cemetery By-Laws, Constitution, and Rules, 1895-1993 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - B'nai Israel Rosters, 1953-2019 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Purchase of Cemetery for Temple B'nai Israel at the Corner of Trinity and Vine, Victoria, TX, 1900-10 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - B'nai Israel Donation List and Letters, 1989-2015 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - B'nai Israel Congregational Meetings and Agendas, 1990-2016 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Congregation B'nai Israel Annual Meetings and Budgets, 1991-04-2018-09 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - B'nai Israel Directories, 1991-2016 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - B'nai Israel and Cemetery By-Laws, Constitution, and Rules, 1993-09-19 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Series II: Books, 1967
  - "You Can't Live All Your Life: a Story of Fannie Lack", 1967 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - History of Abraham Levi and Founding of Early Victorian Businesses (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Series III: Correspondences, 1995-2019
  - Student Rabbi Letters from Hebrew Union College to B'nai Israel, 1995-2004 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Letters from Melvin Lack and Janna Weiner to B'nai Israel Temple Members, 1995-2005 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Letters on Rabbi Sandy Shapiro and Student Rabbis, 1999-08-2000-02 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Letter from Melvin Mack to City Manager Denny Arnold, 2001-07-12 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Blessing and Assistance to Sick Members of B'nai Israel, 2003-2013 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Resumes for the Position of Rabbi at B'nai Israel, 2006-2019 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Donations of B'nai Israel Papers to Texas Jewish Historical Review, 2011-06-29 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Series IV: News-clippings, 1914-2010
  - Founding and Early Presidents of B'nai Israel, 1914-1968 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Simon Levy Family Reunion News-clippings, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Obituaries of Former B'nai Israel Members, 1930-2008 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - History of Victoria's First Churches, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Jewish Pioneers and Descendants of Victoria and South Texas, 1974-2005 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Reopening of Temple B'nai Israel, 1989-09-29 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Houston Chronicle Article on the Closing of Temple Shearith Israel, 2002-02 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Rabbi Deborah Schloss Accepts Position at B'nai Israel, 2005-08 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Interview of Rabbi Shira Lander on Early Jewish History, 2010-05 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Biographies of August and Simon Levy (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Levy-Wormster and Westheimer-Levy Marriage News-clippings (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Series V: Photographs, 1900-2019
  - Flash-drive containing B'nai Israel Gravestone Photos, 1900-2019 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Scope and Contents
    Flashdrive contains 330 images of gravestones in B'nai Israel cemetery in Victoria, Texas.
  - Photos of Several Victoria Bankers, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Photo of Ark at B'nai Israel, 1989-12-03 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Series VI: Programs/Flyers, 1877-2005
  - Fifth Annual Masquerade of the Hebrew Benevolent Society, Casino Hall, Victoria, TX, 1877-01 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Jewish High Holidays at B'nai Israel, 1951-09 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Address of Godcheaux L. Levi to the Victoria Historical Society and Letters from Godcheaux L. Levi to Melvin Lack, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Newsletters and Events, 1974-2008 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Biography of and Newsletters on Rabbi Norman Kahan, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Temple B'nai Israel Open House and Tour History Script, 1989-12-03 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Texas Jewish Historical Society Newsletters, 1995-2006 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - B'nai Israel Events and Services Schedules, 1996-2014 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - The Victoria Shofar Newsletters, 2003-2008 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Performance of "A Child of Our Time" by The Washington Chorus, 2005-05 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Series VII: History, 1974
  - History of the Founding Fathers of Temple Emanu-El, Dallas, TX, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Pamphlet on The Historical Levi-Welder House, ND (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - History of Temple B'nai Israel by Dr Branfman, ND (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Series VIII: Addenda
  - The Victoria Shofar - Temple B'nai Israel newsletter, 1995-09-1998-04 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - The Victoria Shofar - Temple B'nai Israel newsletter, 1998-05-2000-12 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - The Victoria Shofar - Temple B'nai Israel newsletter, 2001-01-2006-03 (Box 2, Folder 3)